This video is about task 42.
This task is about a Prolog program
where we shall apply a resolution step.
We have been given a Prolog
program which is above here.
It is just four lines of Prolog code.
We have been given a query and we
shall apply one resolution step.
Therefore we have two specific tasks: first
of all we shall use add(Z2, Y2, s(0)) as L
and in the second part we shall
use mult(X2, Y2, U2) as L.
In the first task we also use the second
program clause only – so this one.
And then in the other part we use
the third program clause only.
Okay, let's start with the first part of the
task which is using add(Z2, Y2, s(0)) as L.
This is our L and it is the first part of the
query and we call the remainder of the query Q
– these are all the the other expressions.
And we have chosen the second program clause.
That's that's this one here.
L_0 is the left-hand side of the clause and
L_1 is the right hand side in this case.
If there would be other expressions like
being separated with comma – like below
here – we would have an L_2 and if there would
be more than even L_3 and so on and so far.
Now our first step for the resolution step is
finding the most general unifier for L and L_0.
This is the unification of those two expressions.
In fact we have to rename X, Y, and Z
– this is just to be sure that we have fresh
variables when applying the program clause.
So we choose new variables here for X,
Y, and Z – we just add a 1 in this case.
Then we have fresh variables.
Now we can unify the expression by
matching every part of the expression.
add has to be matched to add and it
has three parameters in both cases.
We have to match Z2 to s(X_1)
and Z2 to Y_1 and s(0) to s(Z_1).
We get a replacement for the variables
which is our most general unifier.
When we do this, we have two options.
In the first case we have
to replace Z2 by s(X_1) – so
that's what we have to do and
also Z_1 has to be replaced by 0.
But we can choose to replace Y2 by Y_1 or Y_1
by Y2 – so that's why we have two options.
Now we have our most general unifiers.
And we can continue with the resolution step.
We take all the Ls beside zero –
so all L with numbers besides zero.
So in this case it's only L_1.
We could have L_2 and L_3 and so on and so far
but it's only L_1 so we take this
one and our most general unifiers.
So we have our most general unifiers of
the first option of most general unifier
our second option and we have the L_1.
But it's not correct in that sense at the
moment because when we searched for a most
general unifier we renamed all the variables here
so we have to apply this renaming here as well.
So we replace X by X_1, Y by Y_1, and Z
by Z_1 – that's what we have to do here.
This is an ingredient for our
resolution step but we also require Q.
Q does not change but we have to add
it to our query so we add Q here.
We take it as it is together
with our L_1 with the renamings.
And now we apply our most general unifiers.
In the first case we replace Z2 by
s(X_1), Y2 by Y_1, and Z_1 with 0.
So it happens in all these
expressions and in the second case
we do the same but we replace Y_1 with Y2.
And when we do this then we get two
possible queries that we can have.
And we see that these expressions
are the same besides renaming.
If we choose Y_1 for our variable
then it's the first expression –
or we can have for the same variable
Y2 – and that's the second expression.
We see this also in our most general unifier.
That's was the choice we had.
But besides Y_1 and Y2 these queries are the same.
These are our final queries
for the first part of our task.
Now we come to our second part.
This time we choose another L.
We have also another line of
our Prolog code that we choose.
In this case it's the third line.
We choose L as mult(X2, Y2, U2).
That's what was given in the task.
When we choose those, then it results that
our P is in this case this expression.
So P is everything before L.
It's a sequence of such expressions.
We have in this case it's these two expressions.
Now our first step for the
resolution step in this case is again
finding the most general unifier of L and L_0.
We use a unification step.
We rename the variable again.
I add a one here in this case again to Y.
This renaming is just in case if there is a
variable with the same name within the expression.
I just always choose a fresh name.
So we have got a fresh name
now for all the variables.
In this case it's just this single Y.
Now we do a unification again.
We have to match this mult with mult
and then all the three parameters.
We get again two possible most general unifiers.
In both cases X2 is replaced by
zero and U2 is replaced by zero.
And in one case Y2 is replaced by Y_1 and
in the other case Y_1 is replaced by Y2.
Now we take those most general unifiers.
In this case we do not have L_1.
This is a fact and thus we do
not have L_1 one available.
But still we have P available.
So we have to to choose P here.
We can simplify the clauses – we do not have the
right hand side within our
program here, because of the fact.
So our query is reduced to that.
Now we apply our most general unifiers.
In the first case we replace X2 by 0.
– Or well – we do it in both
cases, but there is no X2!
Nevertheless it's part of
our most general unifier.
So nothing changes for that, but we
replace Y2 with Y_1 in the first case
and in the other case we replace Y_1 with
Y2 which does not change anything here.
Lastly we replace U2 with zero in both cases.
Now we get a new query.
If we have chosen the first most
general unifier we get this query.
If we have chosen the second most general
unifier then we get this query here as result.
We are done with our resolution step
and we are done with the complete task.
So we have made a resolution step
for the second program clause and
choosing L as add(Z2, Y2, s(0)).
And we've done a resolution step for the third
program clause and choosing L as mult(X2, Y2, U2)